Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Humanitarian Action and Response, 2000 -- 2004; UA197.019; 4 Digital Object(s)
    - The International Operational Response to the Psychological Wounds of War: Understanding and Improving the Psycho-social Interventions, 2002-01-25; UA197.019.019.00004; McDonald, Laura
      The character of intra- and inter-state conflict has changed dramatically in recent decades. Prior to the Second World War, conflict victims were predominantly found between "established fighting units such as government military troops and armed opposition groups."1 Today, however, conflicts inflict their greatest harm on civilian populations, 80% of whom are women and children. In the 1990s alone, civilian populations endured nearly 90% of the casualties resulting from war representing a sharp increase from approximately 5% in the 1930s only 60 years prior.2 The practice of civilian targeting has resulted in mass population movements, or forcible displacement, on a scale previously unknown. In 1999, an estimated 7 million people were driven from their homes by war, civil insurgency or political repression, which "increased the world's uprooted population to 35 million, 14 million of which were refugees."3 This has taken a huge physical and psychological toll on war-affected individuals and their societies.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Psychotherapy; Feinstein International Center
  - M.A. in Humanitarian Assistance, 2003; UA197.020; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the M.A. in Humanitarian Assistance project.
    - Towards a New Curriculum for Humanitarian Studies? Report on Workshop, 2003-10-22; UA197.020.020.00001; Feinstein International Center
      In April 2002 the Feinstein International Famine Center applied for a renewal of a grant from the Andrew Mellon Foundation to support its work in teaching and research on humanitarian issues. One of the proposed outcomes from the grant was to initiate a discussion with other universities that are teaching similar courses to explore areas of convergence, research and teaching methodologies and other aspects relating to the development of what is now a growing field or sub- field called "Humanitarian Studies".
      Universities and colleges--Graduate work; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
  - Practitioner Expert Program, 1998; UA197.021; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Practitioner Expert Program project.
    - Bosnia-Herzgovina: Basic Themes from a Complex Emergency, 1998-01-01; UA197.021.021.00001; Knight, Tim
      The breakup of the former Yugoslavia, and particularly the humanitarian disaster that Bosnia-Herzegovina became (and still is, for many), offers an excellent "case study" of a complex emergency. Several themes and conclusions may be drawn which may address the issues above and help the humanitarian assistance community prepare for, and respond to, future complex emergencies.
      Humanitarian Assistance; Emergencies; Feinstein International Center
  - The BRIDGES Project, 2011; UA197.022; 2 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the BRIDGES project.
    - Conflict in the Somali Region of Ethiopia: Can Education Promote Peace-Building?, 2011-06-15; UA197.022.022.00001; Richards, Simon; Bekele, Gezu
      This report is an analysis of the links between conflict and education in Somali Region, and examines if and how improved education might contribute to peace and security objectives. While recognizing the critical role of education in the development of the region, the analysis questions a causal framework in which improved education alone will lead to short-term or long-term conflict transformation. This finding is related to the deep-rooted and complex causes of conflict in the region, and the reality that current education services do not engage directly with the main conflict actors. The report makes recommendations for reshaping education strategies to enhance possible impact on conflict.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Primary education; Feinstein International Center
    - The Role of Education in Livelihoods in the Somali Region of Ethiopia, 2011-07-14; UA197.022.022.00002; Jackson, Elanor
      This report seeks to understand people's perceptions of the past and future role of education in the livelihoods of people in the Somali Region of Ethiopia, including the livelihoods of pastoralists, of those exiting pastoralism and those seeking to diversify their livelihoods.
  - Response Analysis in Food Security Crises, 2012; UA197.023; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Response Analysis in Food Security Crises project.
    - Response Analysis: What Drives Program Choice?, 2012-11-01; UA197.023.023.00001; Maxwell, Daniel; Stobaugh, Heather; This research considers "response analysis": the analytical process by which the objectives and modality of program response options in an emergency are determined. The research question was whether improved analysis drives program response choices in humanitarian food security interventions?
      Food security; Subsistence economy; Economies and societies in transition; Feinstein International Center
  - Winning Hearts and Minds? Understanding the Relationship between Aid and Security, 2012; UA197.024; 2 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Winning Hearts and Minds? project.
    - Winning Hearts and minds in Uruzgan Province, 2012-09-01; UA197.024.024.00001; Fishstein, Paul; Research in Uruzgan suggests that insecurity is largely the result of the failure of governance, which has exacerbated traditional tribal rivalries. While respondents within the international military did report some short-term benefits of aid projects in facilitating interaction with and collecting information from communities, it appears that corruption, tribal politics, and the heavy-handed behavior of international forces neutralized whatever positive effects aid projects might have delivered.
      Uruzgan (Afghanistan); Humanitarian Assistance; Surety of the peace; Political stability; Nation-building; Feinstein International Center
    - Afghanistan: Humanitarianism in uncertain times, 2012-12-01; UA197.024.024.00002; Benelli, Prisca; This report focuses on the lives and vulnerabilities of those affected by the crisis and on the attempts by local and international agencies to mitigate these vulnerabilities within the fraught and volatile Afghan context. It presents an analysis of the humanitarian situation on the ground and of the challenges and constraints faced by the humanitarian community in a fast-moving environment. Its conclusions point to urgent changes required to improve the response to a severe and deepening humanitarian crisis and to protect humanitarian agencies, to the extent possible, from overt politicization and manipulation.
      Afghanistan; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
  - Food by Prescription, 2012; UA197.025; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Food by Prescription project.
    - Food by Prescription, 2012-12-01; UA197.025.025.00001; Sadler, Kate; Bontrager, Elizabeth; Rogers, Beatrice; Coates, Jennifer; Ghosh, Shibani; Kidane, Yitbarek; Suri, Devika; Passarelli, Simone; Great strides have been made over the last 20 years in the long-term management of HIV infection in developing countries, resulting in improved immune function, reduced mortality, and prolonged survival. However, underlying malnutrition continues to impede positive health outcomes, and HIV infection in turn worsens malnutrition. The Ethiopia Food by Prescription (FBP) program, implemented by Save the Children US (SC US), USAID/Ethiopia, and the Ethiopian Ministry of Health since 2010, provides therapeutic food along with nutritional assessment and counseling to malnourished HIV+ individuals. The Tufts University Friedman School of Nutrition Science and Policy was contracted by SC US to research the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of this intervention, in order to contribute much needed evidence to guide programming and policy, both in Ethiopia and worldwide.
      Ethiopia; Malnutrition; HIV; Feinstein International Center
  - Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas, 2013; UA197.026; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas project.
    - Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas: Case Study Israel, 2013-02-01; UA197.026.026.00001; Refugees in urban areas face a specific set of livelihoods problems, and in recent years many aid agencies have begun to try to address these problems by supporting refugees through vocational training, microcredit and other services. So far, however, there has been little evidence about which humanitarian programs work, and where opportunities for programming interventions lie. This study, funded by the US State Department's Bureau of Population, Refugees and Migration, addresses this knowledge gap. Through case studies in Cairo, Tel Aviv and Quito, we analyzed the urban livelihoods context for refugees and identified programming opportunities and promising program initiatives. In each city, we sought to generate new ideas from related fields of inquiry, such as low-income urban development and youth employment,that could be adapted for refugees in countries of first asylum.
      Israel; Livelihood and environment; Refugees; Urban Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas: Case Study Ecuador, 2013-02-01; UA197.026.026.00002; Refugees in urban areas face a specific set of livelihoods problems, and in recent years many aid agencies have begun to try to address these problems by supporting refugees through vocational training, microcredit and other services. So far, however, there has been little evidence about which humanitarian programs work, and where opportunities for programming interventions lie. This study, funded by the US State Department's Bureau of Population, Refugees and Migration, addresses this knowledge gap. Through case studies in Cairo, Tel Aviv and Quito, we analyzed the urban livelihoods context for refugees and identified programming opportunities and promising program initiatives. In each city, we sought to generate new ideas from related fields of inquiry, such as low-income urban development and youth employment,that could be adapted for refugees in countries of first asylum.
      Ecuador; Livelihood and environment; Refugees; Urban Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas: Case Study Egypt, 2013-02-01; UA197.026.026.00003; Refugees in urban areas face a specific set of livelihoods problems, and in recent years many aid agencies have begun to try to address these problems by supporting refugees through vocational training, microcredit and other services. So far, however, there has been little evidence about which humanitarian programs work, and where opportunities for programming interventions lie. This study, funded by the US State Department's Bureau of Population, Refugees and Migration, addresses this knowledge gap. Through case studies in Cairo, Tel Aviv and Quito, we analyzed the urban livelihoods context for refugees and identified programming opportunities and promising program initiatives. In each city, we sought to generate new ideas from related fields of inquiry, such as low-income urban development and youth employment,that could be adapted for refugees in countries of first asylum.
      Egypt; Livelihood and environment; Refugees; Urban Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - Refugee Livelihoods in Urban Areas: Identifying Program Opportunities, 2013-02-01; UA197.026.026.00004; Refugees in urban areas face a specific set of livelihoods problems, and in recent years many aid agencies have begun to try to address these problems by supporting refugees through vocational training, microcredit and other services. So far, however, there has been little evidence about which humanitarian programs work, and where opportunities for programming interventions lie. This study, funded by the US State Department's Bureau of Population, Refugees and Migration, addresses this knowledge gap. Through case studies in Cairo, Tel Aviv and Quito, we analyzed the urban livelihoods context for refugees and identified programming opportunities and promising program initiatives. In each city, we sought to generate new ideas from related fields of inquiry, such as low-income urban development and youth employment,that could be adapted for refugees in countries of first asylum.
      Egypt; Ecuador; Israel; Livelihood and environment; Refugees; Urban Refugees; Feinstein International Center
  - ACAPS Operational Learning, 2013; UA197.027; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the ACAPS Operational Learning project.
    - The Use of Evidence in Humanitarian Decision Making, 2013-02-01; UA197.027.027.00001; Stobaugh, Heather; Walker, Peter; Maxwell, Daniel; Darcy, James; The study is based around three main questions. First, how do decision makers in the humanitarian sector currently use information and analysis? Second, what factors, other than information and analysis, are influential in making decisions? Third, what would enable better-informed response decisions? In order to address these overarching questions, the study looks first at some of the main processes of decision-making in the humanitarian sector and the factors that appear to have most influence on decisions of different kinds. It goes on to look at the way information and analysis is currently generated in the humanitarian sector—both through formal and informal means—and related questions of relevance and credibility. These two topics are then brought together in addressing the question of the use of information by decision makers, and what might enable more informed and evidence-based response decisions.
      Evidence-based practice in social work; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
  - People First! Justice, Accountability, and Reparation in the Greater North of Uganda, 2013; UA197.028; 1 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the People First! Justice, Accountability, and Reparation in the Greater North of Uganda project.
    - They Were Just Thrown Away, and Now the World is Spoiled, 2013-03-01; UA197.028.028.00001; Proctor, Keith; In the aftermath of violence, proper treatment of the dead provides a vital consolation for survivors and their communities. This recognition of the bonds that tie the living to the dead has become a key feature of international human rights, encapsulated in the United Nations' Basic Principles and Guidelines on the Right to a Remedy and Reparation for Victims of Gross Violations of International Human Rights Law and Serious Violations of International Humanitarian Law. But in the case of mass killings and mass graves, there may be no consensus on what "proper treatment" of the dead entails. Drawing on interviews conducted in 2011 with survivors and leaders from Barlonyo, Uganda – the site of a large-scale massacre perpetrated by the Lord's Resistance Army in 2004 – this report analyzes how rapid cultural transformations have complicated what proper treatment of the dead entails, and, therefore, the right to satisfaction. By paying careful attention to how death and remembrance rituals have changed over time among the Langi, the report sets out to provide a set of recommendations based on community priorities for the treatment of those who have died as a result of mass violence; and, offer insights into the cultural context in which any future programming around the proper treatment and memorialization of those killed would be undertaken.
      Uganda; Human rights; Violence; Feinstein International Center
- 2015 accessions, 2013 -- 2015; UA197.003.000002; 41 Digital Object(s)
  This series is arranged in received order.
  This series is open for research.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by the Feinstein International Center, 2015, accessions 2016.049, 2016.053, 2016.059, and 2016.062.
  This series contains publications of the Feinstein Internatioal Center, including white papers, working papers, briefing papers, and annual reports.
  - Livestock, Livelihoods, and Disaster Response: Part One: A Review of Livestock-Based Livelihood Projects in Sudan, 2013; UA197.003.00001; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.8 Megabytes
    Livestock, Livelihoods, and Disaster Response: Part One: A Review of Livestock-Based Livelihood Projects in Sudan, by Merry Fitzpatrick and Helen Young
  - Standing Wealth: Pastoralist Livestock Production and Local Livelihoods in Sudan, 2013; UA197.003.00002; 1 Digital Object(s); 6.3 Megabytes
    Standing Wealth: Pastoralist Livestock Production and Local Livelihoods in Sudan, by Kratli et al
  - Annual Report 2012-2013, UA197.003.00003; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.8 Megabytes
    Annual Report 2012-2013
  - Modern Challenges to Traditional Justice: The Struggle to Deliver Remedy and Reparation in War-Affected Lango, 2013; UA197.003.00004; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.9 Megabytes
    Modern Challenges to Traditional Justice: The Struggle to Deliver Remedy and Reparation in War-Affected Lango, by Teddy Atim and Keith Proctor
  - "They Were Just Thrown Away, and Now the World Is Spoiled": Mass Killing and Cultural Rites in Barlonyo, 2013; UA197.003.00005; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.1 Megabytes
    "They Were Just Thrown Away, and Now the World Is Spoiled": Mass Killing and Cultural Rites in Barlonyo, by Keith Proctor
  - Livelihood Dynamics in Northern Karamoja: A Participatory Baseline Study for the Growth Health and Governance Program, 2013; UA197.003.00006; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.9 Megabytes
    Livelihood Dynamics in Northern Karamoja: A Participatory Baseline Study for the Growth Health and Governance Program, by John Burns, Gezu Bekele, and Darlington Akabwai
  - Structural Violence and Social Suffering among Marginal Nepali Migrants, 2013; UA197.003.00007; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.55 Megabytes
    Structural Violence and Social Suffering among Marginal Nepali Migrants, by Antonio Donini, Jeevan Raj Sharma, and Sanjaya Aryal
  - Livestock, Livelihoods, and Disaster Response: Part Two: Three Cases of Livestock Emergency Programmes in Sudan, and Lessons Learned, 2013; UA197.003.00008; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.55 Megabytes
    Livestock, Livelihoods, and Disaster Response: Part Two: Three Cases of Livestock Emergency Programmes in Sudan, and Lessons Learned, by Getachew Gebru et al
  - Disaster Risk Reduction and Livelihoods, 2013; UA197.003.00009; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.15 Megabytes
    Disaster Risk Reduction and Livelihoods, by Karen Jacobsen et al
  - Urban Profiling of Refugee Situations in Delhi, 2013; UA197.003.00010; 1 Digital Object(s); 5.93 Megabytes
    Urban Profiling of Refugee Situations in Delhi, by Karen Jacobsen et al
  - Ransom, Collaborators, Corruption: Sinai Trafficking and Transnational Networks from Eritrea to Israel. A Case Study of the Eritrean Migration System, 2013; UA197.003.00011; 1 Digital Object(s); .96 Megabytes
    Ransom, Collaborators, Corruption: Sinai Trafficking and Transnational Networks from Eritrea to Israel. A Case Study of the Eritrean Migration System, by Karen Jacobsen, Sara Robinson, and Laurie Lijnders
  - How Do Different Indicators of Household Food Security Compare? Empirical Evidence from Tigray, 2013; UA197.003.00012; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.85 Megabytes
    How Do Different Indicators of Household Food Security Compare? Empirical Evidence from Tigray, by Daniel Maxwell, Jennifer Coates, and Bapu Vaitla
  - Making Gender-Just Remedy and Reparation Possible: Upholding the Rights of Women and Girls in the Greater North of Uganda, 2013; UA197.003.00013; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.5 Megabytes
    Making Gender-Just Remedy and Reparation Possible: Upholding the Rights of Women and Girls in the Greater North of Uganda, by Dyan Mazurana et al
  - Turning Cold Money Hot: What The SHG Movement Can Learn From An Alternate Approach, 2013; UA197.003.00014; 1 Digital Object(s); .28 Megabytes
    Turning Cold Money Hot: What The SHG Movement Can Learn From An Alternate Approach, by Kim Wilson
  - Pastoralism in Practice: Monitoring Livestock Mobility in Contemporary Sudan, 2013; UA197.003.00015; 1 Digital Object(s); 4.9 Megabytes
    Pastoralism in Practice: Monitoring Livestock Mobility in Contemporary Sudan, by Helen Young et al
  - Taking Root: The Cash Crop Trade in Darfur, 2013; UA197.003.00016; 1 Digital Object(s); 5.5 Megabytes
    Taking Root: The Cash Crop Trade in Darfur, by Margie Buchanan-Smith et al
  - Pastoralism in Practice: Monitoring Livestock Mobility in Contemporary Sudan Briefing Paper, 2013; UA197.003.00017; 1 Digital Object(s); .79 Megabytes
    Pastoralism in Practice: Monitoring Livestock Mobility in Contemporary Sudan Briefing Paper, by Helen Young et al
  - Resilience, Food Security Dynamics, and Poverty Traps in Northern Ethiopia Analysis of a Biannual Panel Dataset, 2011-2013, UA197.003.00018; 1 Digital Object(s); 1.66 Megabytes
    Resilience, Food Security Dynamics, and Poverty Traps in Northern Ethiopia Analysis of a Biannual Panel Dataset, 2011-2013, by Daniel Maxwell et al
  - Experiences of National Governments in Expanding Their Role in Humanitarian Preparedness and Response, 2014; UA197.003.00019; 1 Digital Object(s); 6.59 Megabytes
    Experiences of National Governments in Expanding Their Role in Humanitarian Preparedness and Response, by Jeremy Harkey
  - Recovery in Northern Uganda: How are people surviving postconflict?, 2014; UA197.003.00020; 1 Digital Object(s); .29 Megabytes
    Recovery in Northern Uganda: How are people surviving postconflict? Briefing Paper 4, by Dyan Mazurana and Teddy Atim
  - Mapping Evidence Syntheses in the Humanitarian Sector: Insights and Challenges, 2015; UA197.003.00021; 1 Digital Object(s); .22 Megabytes
    Mapping Evidence Syntheses in the Humanitarian Sector: Insights and Challenges, by Kristin Bushby and Roxanne Krystalli
  - Guidance For Profiling Urban Displacement Situations: Challenges And Solutions. Joint IDP Profiling Service, 2014; UA197.003.00022; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.02 Megabytes
    Guidance For Profiling Urban Displacement Situations: Challenges And Solutions. Joint IDP Profiling Service, by Karen Jacobsen and Ivan Cardona
  - Livelihoods, access to services and perceptions of governance: An analysis of Uror and Nyirol counties, South Sudan, 2014; UA197.003.00023; 1 Digital Object(s); .62 Megabytes
    Livelihoods, access to services and perceptions of governance: An analysis of Uror and Nyirol counties, South Sudan. Report 3, by Daniel Maxwell et al
  - Breaking the Hourglass: Partnerships in Remote Management Settings—The Cases of Syria and Iraqi Kurdistan, 2015; UA197.003.00024; 1 Digital Object(s); .74 Megabytes
    Breaking the Hourglass: Partnerships in Remote Management Settings—The Cases of Syria and Iraqi Kurdistan, by Kimberly Howe, Elizabeth Stites, and Danya Chudacoff
  - From post-conflict recovery and state building to a renewed humanitarian emergency: A brief reflection on South Sudan, 2014; UA197.003.00025; 1 Digital Object(s); .47 Megabytes
    From post-conflict recovery and state building to a renewed humanitarian emergency: A brief reflection on South Sudan. Discussion Paper 1, by Daniel Maxwell and Martina Santschi
  - In the eye of the storm: An analysis of internal conflict in South Sudan's Jonglei State, 2014; UA197.003.00026; 1 Digital Object(s); .48 Megabytes
    In the eye of the storm: An analysis of internal conflict in South Sudan's Jonglei State. Working Paper 11, by Rachel Gordon